<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ros on technical_</title><link>https://blog.agramakov.me/categories/ros/</link><description>Recent content in ros on technical_</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.agramakov.me/categories/ros/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Zakhar's Concept</title><link>https://blog.agramakov.me/posts/2019/06-01-zakhars-concept/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.agramakov.me/posts/2019/06-01-zakhars-concept/</guid><description>It is not a secret for anybody, what we are living in the era of consumption. We produce and consume food, medical preparations and of course, the flagship of the planet&amp;rsquo;s economics - electronics. Modern electronics are becoming more and more sophisticated, hard to understand and we have to spend time to learn it. It so, because there is a huge gap between the level of development of technics (which the main face is electronics) and user interfaces.</description></item><item><title>Zakhar relaunch: Zakha_ros</title><link>https://blog.agramakov.me/posts/2019/05-05-zakhar-relaunch-zakha_ros/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.agramakov.me/posts/2019/05-05-zakhar-relaunch-zakha_ros/</guid><description>&lt;p>After a lot of experiments with Raspberry, ESP32, STM32 and Arduino boards I&amp;rsquo;ve decided what will be a spine of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/an-dr/zakhar" target="_blank">Zakhar&lt;/a> project. &lt;a href="https://www.ros.org/" target="_blank">ROS&lt;/a> seems the most interesting and extendible. Inside it, I could combine Python, C, C++ programs (hence, libraries ) working inside a Linux environment and communicate with any other platforms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Say, I could build a system on a Raspberry, which will communicate with developer board like &lt;a href="https://www.espressif.com/en/products/hardware/esp-wrover-kit/overview" target="_blank">ESP-WROVER-KIT&lt;/a> working on FreeRTOS. Even more, I could use my desktop as a part of the system for High-level computing (say, for image recognition with OpenCV).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have bought some hardware for the new version of Zakhar, called &lt;strong>Zakha_ros:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>